<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Selected sentences out of sacred antiquitie, conducing to the establishment of faith and good manners. Gathered by W. Wynne</title>
            <author>Wynne, William, fl. 1616-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106616</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842329</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842329</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6974</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15800)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6974)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 583:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Selected sentences out of sacred antiquitie, conducing to the establishment of faith and good manners. Gathered by W. Wynne</title>
                  <author>Wynne, William, fl. 1616-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. A[llde] for Nathaniell Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes "Short prayers or meditations vpon the last thinges", pages 67-72, which are presumably by Wynne.</note>
                  <note>Leaf A1 blank except for signature.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6974:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6974:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SELECTED SENTENCES OVT OF SACRED ANTIQVITIE, CONDVCING TO the eſtabliſhment of Faith and good Manners. <hi>Gathered by</hi> W. WYNNE.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>E. A.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniell Butter.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6974:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6974:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Honorable, <hi>Sir</hi> HENRY HOWARD Knight of the Hon: Order of the <hi>Bath,</hi> Lord <hi>Matrauers,</hi> Sonne and Heyre apparant of the moſt Hon: the Earle of <hi>Arundell,</hi> Lord High Marſhall of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Hon:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR Thrice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble Brother and my moſt honored Lord and Patron, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now a Celeſtiall Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, and crowned with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Glory among the
<pb facs="tcp:6974:3"/>Princes in Paradiſe, hath left your Lordſhip behind him, not onely to enioy his Honourable titles and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes heere vpon earth, but withall, to tread the pathes of his exemplar Virtue and Nobleneſſe, where through you may finally arriue to the height of his felicitie in Heauen. My true deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beeing tyed to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall memory of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable name, and therein alſo to your Lordſhip as the ſucceeding heyre to all his moſt worthy attributes and rights, doth juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act from mee ſome tribute,
<pb facs="tcp:6974:3"/>or token of my bounden Dutie; which I thus hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſent vnder theſe few memorials gathered out of Sacred Antiquitie; not preſuming thereby, to adde any thing by way of ſupply to thoſe perfections you haue already attained, but rather very humbly cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing your fauorable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance &amp; Honorable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of them, to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of ſome others mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier inſtructed, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, may peraduenture bee the eaſilier induced to peruſe them: For if your Lordſhip deigne to patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize
<pb facs="tcp:6974:4"/>them, who will alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether diſpiſe them? Such therefore as they are, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate and conſecrate, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with my ſelfe, to be for euer:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Humbly at your Lordſhips ſeruice and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> William Wynne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6974:4"/>
            <head>To all my beneuolent Friends and fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat Workes of Penne, proceed from much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience: yet the greateſt are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily brought to pithie abridgement, contayning the ſinewes and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of that bigge Body, and by compendious regularity, are fitter for memory, eaſier for price, and more portable for vſe: This briefe Collection, aymes at no outward practice, not comming from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vertue to enable religious Conſtancy of minde, that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of life, it may bring forth fruits of Pietie and Ciuilitie:
<pb facs="tcp:6974:5"/>There is no Sentence without waight; Exerciſe of one will draw on an eaſie habit to the reſt: which as I wiſh to all, ſo I commend to all; deſiring that the endeauour may paſſe with good Conſtruction, and the vſe to both iſſues of inward Deuotion and outward Practiſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6974:5"/>
            <head>SELECTED SENTENCES OVT of Sacred Antiquitie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Faith and good Manners.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A loue principium.</head>
               <p>GOD is all in all to you: If you hunger, hee is Bread; if you thirſt, hee is Drinke; if you ſit in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hee is Light; if you be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6974:6"/>hee is a garment of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>God is the true and chiefeſt life; in whom, from whom, and by whom, all thinges created are bleſſed and made good. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3.</head>
               <p>It is God from whom to bee auerted is to fall; to whom to bee conuerted is to ariſe; in whom to abide, is to ſtand faſt; from whom to depart, is to dye; to whom to returne, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue; It is God whom no man leeſeth, but he that is deceiued; no man ſeeketh but hee that is taught; no man findeth but hee that is cleane. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4.</head>
               <p>There is no refuge from God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6974:6"/>diſpleaſed, but to God plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5.</head>
               <p>God is neuer wanting; yet farre from his Enemies thoughts: neither when he is farre off is hee wanting: for where hee is not by Grace, he is there by Iuſtice; God is euery where preſent and can hardly be found; we purſue him ſtanding, but are vnable to apprehend him. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>6.</head>
               <p>As there is no Time, wherein wee enioy not the benefits of Gods mercy and goodneſſe, ſo ſhould there bee no moment without remembrance of his preſence: for all Time wherein God is not remembred, wee muſt reckon as vtterly loſt. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6974:7"/>
               <head>7.</head>
               <p>God is all an eye, for he ſeeth all: hee is all a hand, for he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all: hee is all a foote, for he is euery where.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>8.</head>
               <p>Whatſoeuer is beſides GOD, is neither ſweet nor ſauory: whatſoeuer my Lord God will giue mee, let him take it all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine from me, and giue mee himſelfe. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>9.</head>
               <p>Farre bee it from thee (O LORD) that in thy Tabernacle the Rich ſhould be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Poore, or the Noble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ignoble; ſeeing thou madeſt chorſe of the worlds weaklings, to confound the ſtrong and potent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6974:7"/>
               <head>10.</head>
               <p>Affection makes vs doe many thinges with reſpect to bodily neereneſſe: But to offend the Creator of body and ſoule with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect, wee ſticke not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>11.</head>
               <p>I had rather bee blamed of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, then praiſed of a Flatterer; for a louer of Truth is neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of a fault-finder; but a Flatterer, both erres himſelfe, and confirmes others in their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>12.</head>
               <p>Nothing ſo eaſily Corrupts the minde, as Flatterie; yea, more hurt doth the tongue of a Flatterer, then the ſword of a Perſecutor. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>13.</head>
               <p>Ambition is a fooliſh Diſeaſe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6974:8"/>a ſecret Poyſon, a lurking Plague, a worker of Deceit; the mother of Hypocriſie, the begetter of Enuy, the ſpring of Vice, the moath of Holineſſe, the blinder of Hearts; breeding diſeaſes of remedies, and turning medicines into malladies. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>14.</head>
               <p>The Ambition of power, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued an Angell of his Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; the appetite of knowledge robbed Man of his Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>15.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eus</hi> was not beguiled with the Apple, nor did ſhee forget the Commandement, but the Ambition of promiſed Honour beguiled her. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>16.</head>
               <p>Ambition is the Ape of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6974:8"/>Charitie ſuffreth for Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall thinges, Ambition for Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Charitie is benigne to the poore, Ambition to the rich; Charitie ſuſtaines all for veritie, Ambition for vanitie; both of them beleeue all, but after a farre different manner. <hi>Pet. Rauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>17.</head>
               <p>That is euer loſt with much Lament, which is poſſeſt with much Loue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>18.</head>
               <p>There bee two Loues which build vp two Cities: the loue of God builds vp <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> the loue of the world, <hi>Babilon;</hi> Let euery one aske but of himſelfe, what hee loues, and hee ſhall ſoone finde of which Citie hee is. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6974:9"/>
               <head>19.</head>
               <p>The labours of Louers are neuer painefull, but pleaſant; as thoſe of Huntſmen, Faulconers, Fiſhers; for in that wee loue, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we labour not at all, or wee loue our Labour. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>20.</head>
               <p>They are happy that haue all they would haue, and wiſh for no more then what they ſhould haue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>21.</head>
               <p>Peace is not ſought that Warre may come thereof, but warre is made that peace may enſue: Bee you therefore peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in Warre, that you may the better reduce thoſe to Peace, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom you haue gotten victorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:6974:9"/>
               <head>22.</head>
               <p>If the cauſe of Combate bee good, the end can neuer bee ill. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <head>23.</head>
               <p>To bee a Souldier is no fault, but to bee a Souldier for booties ſake, is a ſinne. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>24.</head>
               <p>No leſſe doe they ſinne who blaſpheme CHRIST raigning in Heauen, then did they, who Crucified him walking vpon Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>25.</head>
               <p>The roote of all good is Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, the roote of all euill Cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, theſe two can neuer be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; for vnleſſe the one bee rooted out, the other will neuer be planted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:6974:10"/>
               <head>26.</head>
               <p>Hee verily is a Chriſtian, that worketh Mercy to all; that is mooued with no Iniury; that feeles the griefe of others as his owne; to whoſe Table the Poore is no ſtranger; who is reckoned inglorious before men, that hee may be glorious before GOD and his Angels; who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth Tranſitory thinges to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy Eternall; who ſuffereth not the poore to bee oppreſſed if he can helpe; and to conclude, who weepes with them that weepe: which was well obſerued by St. <hi>Paul, Quis</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>infirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; ego non infirmor?</hi> Who is infirme or grieued, and I not ſo too?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>27.</head>
               <p>In vaine takes hee vpon him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6974:10"/>the name of a Chriſtian, that doth not imitate the life of Chriſt: for (alaſſe) what is it for you to bee called that you are not, or to vſurpe anothers name?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>28.</head>
               <p>A Chriſtian is hee that thinkes himſelfe a Stranger in his owne houſe; our Countrey being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, our home at Heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>29.</head>
               <p>Will you walke? Chriſt ſaith I am the way; will you not bee deceiued? I am the Truth; will you not dye? I am the life. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>30.</head>
               <p>As the many branches of a Tree doe grow from the roote onely, ſo many virtues ſpring from Charitie alone: nor hath the branch of a good worke any life, or greenneſſe, if it abide not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6974:11"/>in the roote of Charitie. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>31.</head>
               <p>Say not that you carry chaſte mindes, when you haue wanton eyes; for a wanton eye is the meſſenger of a wanton heart. <hi>Hierom.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <head>32.</head>
               <p>Among all Chriſtian conflicts thoſe of Chaſtitie are the ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt; for there is continuall bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, and rare victorie; Beautie and Chaſtitie ſeldome lodge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>33.</head>
               <p>Confeſſion is the health of Soules, the deſtroyer of Vices, the ſcourge of Deuils; briefely, it ſtops the mouth of Hell, and opens the gates of Paradice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>34.</head>
               <p>A cleere Conſcience is that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6974:11"/>which can neither bee juſtly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed with what is paſt, nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly delighted with what is preſent. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>35</head>
               <p>Gold is <hi>Caeſars</hi> Coyne, Man is GODS: <hi>Caeſar</hi> is ſeene in his Gold, GOD in Man. Therefore offer your wealth to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but reſerue your Conſcience for GOD. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>36.</head>
               <p>You ſhould rather thinke of what you want, then of that you haue; what you haue beware you leeſe not, and that you want pray God for: Conſider in what you are leſſer, not in how much you are greater; for if you compute onely wherein you are, or haue beene excellent, that may ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6974:12"/>vanitie and pride in you, which is to be feared; but if you reckon wherein you are or haue beene leſſe, or defectiue, this will breed humilitie and teares in you which are to be wiſhed: And doubtleſſe if you ſtriue to bee humble, you ſhall walke more ſafely, you ſhall not runne headlong, your foote ſhall not ſlippe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <head>37.</head>
               <p>God is aboue you, the Beaſts are vnder you: acknowledge him that is aboue you, that they may acknowledge you, which are vnder you: Therefore when <hi>Daniel</hi> acknowledged God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue himſelfe, the Lyons ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged him aboue them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <head>38.</head>
               <p>O Man! if thou didſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6974:12"/>what comes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee by thy mouth, by thine eares, by thy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, by thy pores, &amp; other eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuations of thy body; Thou wouldeſt confeſſe neuer to haue ſeene a more vile and loathſome dunghill, then thy ſelfe. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>39.</head>
               <p>To giue a ſimple man Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell is Charitie; to a Wiſe man Preſumption: but to giue it in caſe of peruerſitie, or neceſſitie is Wiſedome. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <head>40.</head>
               <p>Among the Sages, one was wont to ſay, that a good Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome is neuer diſwonted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhame, and that good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication runnes into affectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all habit: according to that; who fore-goeth Vertue being young, ſhall not know how
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6974:13"/>to forbeare Vice beeing olde. <hi>Baſil.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <head>41.</head>
               <p>Let not your heart vary from your face or Countenance: car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry not a face vpward and a heart downward. The heart is little, and deſireth much; it is ſcarſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to giue a Kite his break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and yet the whole world is not able to ſatisfie it. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <head>42.</head>
               <p>Open Sinne before all, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth open Puniſhment for example of all. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <head>43.</head>
               <p>Impunitie is the of-ſpring of negligence, the mother of Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, the roote of vnſhamefaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Nurſe of Sinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <head>44.</head>
               <p>Couetouſneſſe is the roote of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6974:13"/>all miſchiefe; it commits Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Theft; it rauins and deuoures; it makes warre and murther; it buyes and fels by Symonie; it asketh and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth wrongfully; it negotiates and floords vp vniuſtly; it is at hand with all fraud and deceit; it diſſolues pacts and violates oathes; it corrupts Witneſſe and peruerts Iuſtice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <head>45.</head>
               <p>Three thinges are moſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; Wealth, Pleaſure, and Honour; of Wealth comes wickedneſſe, of Pleaſure turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, of Honour vanitie; for wealth breeds Cupiditie and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice; Pleaſure breeds Luſt and Gluttony, Honour foſtereth Pride and Oſtentation. <hi>Innoc.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:6974:14"/>
               <head>46.</head>
               <p>The Thiefe confeſſed Chriſt, <hi>Peter</hi> denyed him; in <hi>Peter</hi> the Iuſt are taught not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, in the Thiefe: a Sinner conuerted not to deſpaire. Therefore let the Iuſt be off aid of falling through Pride, and the Sinner of deſpairing through malice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <head>47.</head>
               <p>Let no man diſtruſt, nor any ſinner deſpaire of Gods mercy: for God knowes how to change his Iudgment, if you know how to change your life. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <head>48.</head>
               <p>Deſperation holts the gates of the Eternall Citie, Hope vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts them; but Faith ſets them wide open. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6974:14"/>
               <head>49.</head>
               <p>Not onely they are guiltie that vtter falſhood, but ſuch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as eaſily hearken thereunto. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <head>50.</head>
               <p>The heart lifted vp to God corrupteth not; if your Corne were layde in vnder-romes, to ſaue it from moulding, you would remoue it higher: you raiſe your graine to higher loſts, ſo lift vp your hearts to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. But now ſhould this bee done ſay you; what ſtrong Cords, what Ladders, what En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines will bee required to this? Iſay, the firſt ſtep is your affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the leſt of your labour is your will: by Loue you aſcend, by neglect you deſcend, and when you loue God, you are in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6974:15"/>Heauen vpon Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <head>51.</head>
               <p>The Deuill is euery where ready to hurt euery one, but that his power is reſtrained by a greater power; for if he could but what hee would, there ſhould not a Iuſt ſoule bee left to breath. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <head>52.</head>
               <p>The DEuils office is to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt; ours not to conſent: as oft as wee reſiſt euill; ſo oft wee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come it; wee glad and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Angels; wee honour God, who viſites vs that wee may fight, helpeth vs that wee may conquer, and aydes vs that we may not ſhrinke. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="part">
               <head>53.</head>
               <p>O wretch that I am how much am I bound to loue my
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6974:15"/>God, who Created me when I was not, and redeemed me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loſt; for I was not, and hee made me of nothing; yet hee made me not a ſtone, not a tree, not a meere Animal, but a Man: hee gaue mee to liue, to feed, to vnderſtand; hee deliuered me from bondage, redeemed mee from ſeruitude, and called mee by his Name, that I might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="part">
               <head>54.</head>
               <p>CHRIST annoynted mee with the Oyle of gladneſſe, wherewith himſelfe was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted; that of the annoynted I might bee annoynted, and of Chriſt bee called a Chriſtian. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="part">
               <head>55.</head>
               <p>To learne that which is fit, no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6974:16"/>time is to late; and though it become feare Age rather to teach, then to learne, yet it is better to Learne then to beelg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="part">
               <head>56.</head>
               <p>I wiſh, and thinke nothing more fit for mee, then to learne to the laſt houre of my old age: for no Age was euer long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to learne. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="part">
               <head>57.</head>
               <p>By all meanes auoyd chiding or contention in wordes; for with your equall it is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, with your better it is madneſſe; and with your infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour eſpecially with a Foole, it is baſe: and to fall out with him that is Drunke, is to fall out with him that is abſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6974:16"/>
               <head>58.</head>
               <p>Virtue vndiſcreetly poſſeſt, is often loſt; diſcreetly forborne, it is better retayned. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="part">
               <head>59.</head>
               <p>Whatſoeuer you doe well with diſcretion, is Virtue; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer without diſcretion, is Vice; for vndiſcreet virtue, is of no better account then Vice. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="part">
               <head>60.</head>
               <p>If worldly wealth bee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, yet ſeeke it not by any ill meanes in the world; but if you liue in aboundance heere, then lay vp by good workes for your ſelfe elſe-where, in Heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="part">
               <head>61.</head>
               <p>A manly Chriſtian minde, ſhould nener ſhew higher for Wealth, nor lower for Want.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6974:17"/>
               <head>62.</head>
               <p>Gold is liue matter; of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieteſt danger to them that haue it, a bad Lord, and a falſe Seruant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="part">
               <head>63.</head>
               <p>The rich man begging in Hell was not heard, becauſe hee heard not the poore man beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging on Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="part">
               <head>64.</head>
               <p>Earthly riches compared to Heauenly guifts, are rather trouble ſome then comfortable: Temporall life in reſpect of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, sin rather Death then Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="part">
               <head>65.</head>
               <p>When <hi>Diues</hi> was a dying, he had taken all his wealth with him, had hee but giuen to him that asked when he was liuing;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6974:17"/>for all earthly thinges which may bee loſt by keeping, are preſerued by giuing. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="part">
               <head>66.</head>
               <p>Gold and Siluer, in reſpect of the ſoule, are thinges indifferent, neither good nor bad: yet the vſe of them may be good; the abuſe is naught, the Care worſe, the vnlawfull gaine of them worſt of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="part">
               <head>67.</head>
               <p>If Art and vſe bee ſeperated, Vſe is better without Art, then Art without vſe; for Art in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable without vſe, and Vſe vnaduiſed without Art. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="part">
               <head>68.</head>
               <p>If Doctors Preach the Faith, and deale themſelues vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fUlly; they giue peace to others, but none to themſelues; they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6974:18"/>praiſe the truth and practice falſhood; Let vs receiue their Doctrine, not their ill manners: The Bees gather not vpon Weedes, but vpon ſweet Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; ſo let vs gather the flowers of their Doctrine, and leaue the weedes of their Conuerſation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="part">
               <head>69.</head>
               <p>Drankenneſſe is the mother of all miſchiefe, the matter of offence, the roote of vice; it is the Heads perturbation, the Senſes ſubuerſion, the Tongues tempoſt, the Bodies ſtorme, ſhipwracke of Chaſtitie, and loſſe of Time; it is a voluntary madneſſe, a diſgracefull diſeafe, a filthy faſhion, a ſhameleſſe life, the infamy of Honour and Honeſtie, the Soules corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:6974:18"/>
               <head>70.</head>
               <p>Drunkenneſſe is a flattering Deuill, a ſweet Poyſon; a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sinne; hee that hath it hath not himſelfe: he that is Drunke, is not onely a ſinner, but all ſinne himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="part">
               <head>71.</head>
               <p>A Drunkard whilſt he ſoakes in Wine; the Wine ſoakes him: hee is of God abhorred, of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels deſpiſed, of Wertue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, of Men derided, of Deuils confounded, and ſcorned of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="part">
               <head>72.</head>
               <p>A Drunkard deſtroyeth Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, leeſeth Grace, eſcapeth Glory, and incurreth eternall Darnnation. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="part">
               <head>73.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noah</hi> in one houres Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, diſcouered his ſecret
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6974:19"/>parts, which hee had couered ſixe hundred yeares together. <hi>Hierom.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="part">
               <head>74.</head>
               <p>The Church hath this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie; to flouriſh when it is perſecuted, to grow being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, to profit being deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; being beaten it ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, being blamed it vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth; and ſtands faſt when it ſeemes to fall. <hi>Hillar.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="part">
               <head>75.</head>
               <p>If you can giue, giue; if you cannot, yet make your ſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable and willing; for God Crowneth inward willingneſſe; where he findes not out ward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe: Let no man anſwer I haue not for you; Charitie comes not alwayes out of a bagge. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:6974:19"/>
               <head>76.</head>
               <p>If you would bee a good Marchant and an excellent Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter indeed, giue what you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keepe, that you may receiue what you can be leeſe; giue a little to hand much, part with ſomething to gaine an hundred fold, giue a Temporall commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiſe to receiue an Eternall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="part">
               <head>77.</head>
               <p>Who layeth vp his treaſure in Earth, hath nothing to looke for in Heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="part">
               <head>78.</head>
               <p>The hand of the Poore is the treaſury of CHRIST; what the Poore receiueth, CHRIST accepteth. Therefore giue your Land to the Poore, that you may get a Kingdome to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6974:20"/>your ſelfe; giue a Crumme to haue a Crowne; I ſay giue that you may recoine, for whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you giue to the poore, you ſhall bee ſune to haue againe, and that which you will not giue, another ſhall beceine. <hi>Pet. Rouen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="part">
               <head>79.</head>
               <p>It is great impietie to deſhone the goods of the Poore upon the Rich, and to curry fauour with the mightie at the poores coſt; It is to drayne water from the dry ground, and to beſtow it where is no need. <hi>Iſid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="part">
               <head>80.</head>
               <p>I aske you if you beleeue? and you anſwer <hi>Crede,</hi> I doe beleeue: doe as you ſay, and it is beliefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:6974:20"/>
               <head>81.</head>
               <p>Labour not to vnderſtand, that you may beleeue; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that you may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; for vnderſtanding is the fruit and reward of Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="part">
               <head>82.</head>
               <p>Lay arguments aſide where Faith is required: Logicke is now at reſt, and ſilent, in the Schooles, where Fiſhermen are beleeued, not Logicians. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="part">
               <head>83.</head>
               <p>Great is that Glory which increaſeth by no praiſe, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſheth by no diſpraiſe. <hi>Caſſ.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="part">
               <head>84.</head>
               <p>The vaine glory of this world is ſweet and deceiptfull; a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe paine, a perpecuall feare, a perilous Throne; it begins with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6974:21"/>improuidence, and ends with impenitence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="part">
               <head>85.</head>
               <p>The glory is not ſo great of ſitting high, as the griefe is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame in falling lowe; nor ſo much the triumph which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends vpon Victory, as the ſhame and reproach that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth Deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="part">
               <head>86.</head>
               <p>If you loue Wealth, lay it vp where it cannot periſh; if Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, eſteeme it where none are vnworthily honoured; if health, ſpeake to enioy it, where nothing is feared; if Life, then loue it where it cannot end with Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="part">
               <head>87.</head>
               <p>If GOD haue giuen you Grace becauſe hee would giue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6974:21"/>it freely; then Loue you God freely, not for reward, but for himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="part">
               <head>88.</head>
               <p>Why Gods grace is beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon one and not vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Cauſe may bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, but it cannot bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="part">
               <head>89.</head>
               <p>All that is done is loſt, if Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie bed wanting. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="part">
               <head>90.</head>
               <p>Humilitie is a Virtue, by which in knowing, wee learne age eſteeme our ſelues. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="part">
               <head>91.</head>
               <p>Faſting is knowne to bee the Tower of God, the Caſtle of Chriſt, the wall of the Holy Ghoſt, the ſhield of Faith, the tryumph of Sanctitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:6974:22"/>
               <head>92.</head>
               <p>Of that manner of Faſting God well alloweth, by which you take out of your owne mouth, to put into anothers; or by which you afflict your owne Carkaſſe, to relieue your poore Neighbours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="part">
               <head>93.</head>
               <p>Though Faſting expell the ſickneſſe of Vice and Sinne, cuts off Paſſions, and driues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the cauſes of offence; yet without the oyntment of pittie, without the ſtreame of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the coſt of Almes, it brings no perfect health to the Soule: Faſting cureth the wounds of the ſoule, but without mercy, it leaues the ſcarres behinde. <hi>Pet. Rouan.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:6974:22"/>
               <head>94.</head>
               <p>The bleſſed ſhall firſt be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to their prepared Kingdome, before the accurſed bee caſt into their burning Lake, that their ſorrowes may bee the ſharper by ſeeing what they haue loſt, and the luſt haue more joy by conſidering what they haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="part">
               <head>95.</head>
               <p>It is laudable to bee patient in our owne wrongs, but to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the iniuries of God is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="part">
               <head>96.</head>
               <p>Enuy is the Daughter of Pride, and that mother Pride is neuer barren, but euer bearing: ſtrangle that mother, and there will bee no more ſuch Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:6974:23"/>
               <head>97.</head>
               <p>Not to bee ſory after you haue finned, makes God more angry and diſpleaſed, then the ſinne you committed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="part">
               <head>98.</head>
               <p>The ignorance of Iudges for the moſt part, is the miſery of Innocents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="part">
               <head>99.</head>
               <p>I ſay vnto you Sweare not at all; leaſt Swearing breed a faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of ſwearing; facilitie Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and cuſtome lead you to Periurie. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="part">
               <head>100.</head>
               <p>As that Tree hath no fruit which firſt had no bloſſome; ſo that Age hath no honour, whoſe Youth had no Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:6974:23"/>
               <head>101.</head>
               <p>It is no true bountie that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds more from vaine Glory, then from the occaſion of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; for your worke takes it name from your affection. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="part">
               <head>102.</head>
               <p>Very many haue I ſeene fall into ſinne by ſpeaking, but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome any by ſilence; and doubtleſſe, it is harder to learne how to bee ſilent, then how to ſpeake. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="103" type="part">
               <head>103.</head>
               <p>O Infernall wantonneſſe of the Fleſh, whoſe matter is Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, whoſe flame is Pride, whoſe ſparkles are lewd Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, whoſe ſmoake is Infamie, whoſe end is Hell fire. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:6974:24"/>
               <head>104.</head>
               <p>O extreame filthineſſe of luſt; which not onely effeminateth the minde, but enfeebleth the body: not onely ſpotteth the ſoule but polluteth the perſon: All other ſinne which a man committeth, is beſides his body but the Fornicator ſinneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne body. Heat and wantonneſſe march before it: vncleanneſſe and pollution accompany it; Sorrow and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance doe alwayes follow it. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="105" type="part">
               <head>105.</head>
               <p>It is great vertue not to hurt, him that hurts you; it is no leſſe fortitude when you are hurt to forgiue; but to ſpare him whom you may hurt, is great glory, <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="106" type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:6974:24"/>
               <head>106.</head>
               <p>To ſearch the reaſon of Gods ſecret councell, is no other thing then proudly to vaunt againſt his Councell. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="107" type="part">
               <head>107.</head>
               <p>I remember not to haue read of any that dyed an ill death, who had freely vſed the workes of mercy in his life; ſuch a one ſurely hath many interceſſors, and impoſſible it is, that the prayers of many ſhould not bee heard. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="108" type="part">
               <head>108.</head>
               <p>Good men are called away betimes, that they may no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bee vexed of the wicked; and wicked perſons are cut off, that they may perſecute the iuſt no further.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="109" type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:6974:25"/>
               <head>109.</head>
               <p>In ſuch eſtate as euery mans laſt houre leaues him, in the like will the worlds laſt day finde him; for as hee dyeth in the one, ſo ſhall hee bee iudged in the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="110" type="part">
               <head>110.</head>
               <p>Hee cannot Dye ill, that hath Liued well; and hardly can hee dye well, that hath liued ill. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="111" type="part">
               <head>111.</head>
               <p>A Sinner ſhould be aſtoniſht with this note; that when hee dyeth, hee may forget himſelfe, who whileſt hee liued forgot God. <hi>Caeſarius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="112" type="part">
               <head>112.</head>
               <p>To maintaine a poore wife is very hard, to endure a rich one is a torment: what booteth a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6974:25"/>diligent watch? ſeeing a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt woman will not bee kept in, an honeſt ſhould not: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie is but a falſe keeper of Chaſtitie, and ſhee onely is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee reputed chaſte, that might haue ſinned and would not. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="113" type="part">
               <head>113.</head>
               <p>If it bee a ſinne to put away a Wife, and a torment to keepe her, then of neceſſitie wee ſhall incurre danger of Adulteries by the one, and ſuffer continuall brawles by the other. <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="114" type="part">
               <head>114.</head>
               <p>The Fetters of this world are truely rough and troubleſome, the Pleaſures falſe, the Sorrowes certayne, the Ioyes inconſtant, the Labours hard, the Reſt doubtfull, the Wealth accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6974:26"/>with Care, and the hopes of Earthly happineſſe vaine. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="115" type="part">
               <head>115.</head>
               <p>The World proclaimes, <hi>I will fayle you:</hi> The Fleſh cryes out, <hi>I will infeſt you:</hi> The Deuill roares, <hi>I will betray you:</hi> But CHRIST ſaith, <hi>I will refreſh you. Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="116" type="part">
               <head>116.</head>
               <p>Who would not be aſhamed to ſay, What will you giue mee that I may doe you Iuſtice? Is it not as much as to ſay, what will you giue mee to deny my ſelfe, to forget my place, and to ſell God Almighty? <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="117" type="part">
               <head>117.</head>
               <p>A Chriſtians chiefeſt libertie to God-ward, is to bee no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to ſinne; his chiefeſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6974:26"/>to excell in Vertues. <hi>Hierom.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="118" type="part">
               <head>118.</head>
               <p>Prayer is talking to GOD: when you read, God ſpeakes to you; and when you pray, you ſpeake to God; Therefore pray with attention; for the prayer which man intendeth not, God heareth not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="119" type="part">
               <head>119.</head>
               <p>God is neither forced nor mooued by a crying voyce, but pleaſed and appeaſed by an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Conſcience; for hee is a hearer not of the voyce, but of the heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="120" type="part">
               <head>120.</head>
               <p>Many there are whom God heareth not to their intentions, that he may heare them to their ſaluations. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="121" type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:6974:27"/>
               <head>121.</head>
               <p>Whether it bee Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that vſeth wanton attyre to prouoke and tempt others, though no hurt ſhould come thereof, yet hee, or ſhee ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the eternall Iudgement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they proffered Poyſon, if any would haue drunke of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="122" type="part">
               <head>122.</head>
               <p>The onely perfection of any, is the knowledge of their owne imperfection. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="123" type="part">
               <head>123.</head>
               <p>Seeing that Sinne muſt not ſcape vnpuniſhed, puniſh you it, leaſt it puniſh you: euer let your ſinne finde you a Iudge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it, not a Patron for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="124" type="part">
               <head>124.</head>
               <p>Vaine is that Repentance which is ſpotted with enſuing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6974:27"/>ſinne; Laments auayle nothing where ſinne is doubled: It is to no purpoſe to aske forgiueneſſe, and fall into the ſame ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="125" type="part">
               <head>125.</head>
               <p>The practice of right Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, is not to preſume to Command, before wee haue learned to obey; nor to impoſe that vpon our Inferiours, which wee yeeld not to our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="126" type="part">
               <head>126.</head>
               <p>So farre ſhould a Prelates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour tranſcend the Peoples, as a Shepheard tranſcends his Flocke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="127" type="part">
               <head>127.</head>
               <p>If hee ſhall bee caſt into the Fire, that giueth not of his owne, what may wee thinke
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6974:28"/>will become of him that robbes another? If hee burne with the Deuill, that cloathed not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, where ſhall hee burne that ſtrippeth the Poore?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="128" type="part">
               <head>128.</head>
               <p>What you haue found, and not reſtored, you haue carryed away by force; for what you could doe, you did; and you did no more, becauſe you could not; hee alſo that denyeth to another his owne, as much as in him lyes, robbes him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="129" type="part">
               <head>129.</head>
               <p>Sinne is not remitted, vnleſſe debt bee reſtored, if it may bee. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="130" type="part">
               <head>130.</head>
               <p>Wee that liue vpon the obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Faithfull, which they offered for their ſinnes,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6974:28"/>doubtleſſe if wee eate and bee ſilent, we feed vpon their ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="131" type="part">
               <head>131.</head>
               <p>Conſider (O Brethren) how damnable a thing it is, to receiue wage for no worke? what a crime to take the price of ſinne, and to Preach nothing againſt ſinne. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="132" type="part">
               <head>132.</head>
               <p>Whatſoeuer yee retayne of the Altars, beſides ſimple Food and Cloathing; it is rapine, it is Sacriledge. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="133" type="part">
               <head>133.</head>
               <p>Who affirmeth to haue knowledge being ignorant, is raſh; who denyes that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hee hath, is vnthankfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="134" type="part">
               <head>134.</head>
               <p>An Olde mans diſcourſe ſhould not onely bee weightie
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6974:29"/>and graue, but withall ſhort or not very long. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="135" type="part">
               <head>135.</head>
               <p>An Old man heareth the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of Death, and will not beleeue them; the meſſengers are three; Caſualtie, Sickneſſe, and old Age it ſelfe: Caſualtie propounds thinges vncertaine; Sickneſſe thinges ſorrowfull; old Age thinges certaine: Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie ſhewes death lurking; Sickneſſe death appearing; old Age death preſent: From vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie of Death proceeds feare; from paine of Sickneſſe, griefe; and from the certaintie of old Age, ſhould come not obſtinacy and ſtiffeneſſe, but Mortification and Humilitie. <hi>Hug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="136" type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:6974:29"/>
               <head>136.</head>
               <p>The patience to ſay nothing, the oportunitie of ſpeaking, and the contempt of worldly wealth, are the chiefe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="137" type="part">
               <head>137.</head>
               <p>As it becomes not a Biſhop to ſell that hand hee layeth vpon others, ſo the ordayned Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, muſt neither ſet his Tongue nor his Pen to ſale.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="138" type="part">
               <head>138.</head>
               <p>When a Biſhop purchaſeth vndue Order with money, whereby his inward man is caſt off; his Body receiueth honour, and his Soule loſeth honeſtie. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="139" type="part">
               <head>139.</head>
               <p>Euery one is ſo much the more vnwiſe inwardly, as hee
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6974:30"/>ſtriueth to bee thought wiſe outwardly. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="140" type="part">
               <head>140.</head>
               <p>If a Rich man proud, bee ſcarce tollerable, who will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer an inſolent Begger? <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="141" type="part">
               <head>141.</head>
               <p>Pride precipitateth from the higheſt Heauen, to the deepeſt pit of Hell: Humilitie exalteth from below to aboue: an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell fell from Heauen into Hell; Man from Earth aſcendeth to Heauen. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="142" type="part">
               <head>142.</head>
               <p>The vicious for the moſt part, loue ſuch as are like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; onely one proud body, can neuer indure another. <hi>Inno.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="143" type="part">
               <head>143.</head>
               <p>Preſent feare, begets eternall ſecuritie; now feare God aboue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6974:30"/>all thinges, that you need not be affraid of Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="144" type="part">
               <head>144.</head>
               <p>Let Man vnderſtand, that GOD is a Phyſitian, and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation a Medicine to Saluation, not a preparatiue to Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="145" type="part">
               <head>145.</head>
               <p>In the Furnace, Strawe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, Gold purifieth; the one conſumeth to aſhes, the other is purged of droſſe and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the Furnace is the World; the Gold is the luſt; the Fire is Tribulation; the cunning work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is GOD: What the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man willeth I doe; where and when hee appoints I ſuffer: hee that appoints mee to endure, knowes when I ſhall bee pure: though the ſtrawe burne and ſet
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6974:31"/>mee on fire, yet when it is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to aſhes, I ſhall bee cleane without ſpot or ſtaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="146" type="part">
               <head>146.</head>
               <p>Our LORD ſaith Forgiue, and you ſhall bee forgiuen: ſay not with your tongue you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, and differ with your heart; for God knowes what you ſay and thinke together; Man heares what you ſay, but GOD ſees what you thinke: It is much better to forgiue heartily and ſay nothing, then to carry a faire golden mouth, and a falſe froward heart. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="147" type="part">
               <head>147.</head>
               <p>So mercifull is our Lord IESVS, that hee would haue pardoned <hi>Iudas,</hi> if hee had but craued pardon and hoped for CHRISTS mercy. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="148" type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:6974:31"/>
               <head>148.</head>
               <p>O Man! thou canſt not bee without ſinne; and if alwayes thou wilt bee forgiuen all, then forgiue alwayes; how much thou wilt bee forgiuen, ſo much forgiue; how often thou wilt bee forgiuen, ſo often forgiue: yea, and becauſe thou wouldeſt bee forgiuen all, forgiue all: I ſay O man conceiue, that in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing others, thou forgiueſt thy ſelfe. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="149" type="part">
               <head>149.</head>
               <p>Truth is both ſweet and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; ſweet when it ſpareth, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when it cureth. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="150" type="part">
               <head>150.</head>
               <p>What booteth a cleane Body with a corrupt Minde? an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Wife is better then a proud Virgin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="151" type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:6974:32"/>
               <head>151.</head>
               <p>What is the Mindes virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? entire Faith, ſtrong Hope, and perfect Charitie. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="152" type="part">
               <head>152.</head>
               <p>Virginitie ſurpaſſeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of humane nature, by which men are made like vnto Angels: yet greater is the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory of Virgins then of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; for Angels liue without Fleſh, but Virgins triumph in Fleſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="153" type="part">
               <head>153.</head>
               <p>Virginitie is the Siſter of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the Conqueſt of Luſts, the Queene of Vertues, the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Goodneſſe. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="154" type="part">
               <head>154.</head>
               <p>Vertue, the more it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneth, the more it is eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. It is great Vertue to ſtriue
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6974:32"/>with Proſperitie, and great Proſperitie not to bee ouercome by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="155" type="part">
               <head>155.</head>
               <p>The minde can neuer enioy the kingdome of Vertue, vnleſſe it firſt ſhake off the yoake of Vice. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="156" type="part">
               <head>156.</head>
               <p>There is no ſuch perſuaſion, to Vertue, as often to remember the vglineſſe of Sinne. <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="157" type="part">
               <head>157.</head>
               <p>There is nothing well-done, vnwillingly, though the thing done bee neuer ſo good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="158" type="part">
               <head>158.</head>
               <p>If you ſteale not becauſe you are affraid to bee ſeene, yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in your heart you haue ſtolne, and are to bee held guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereof, though you take
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6974:33"/>nothing away. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="159" type="part">
               <head>159.</head>
               <p>When you will you cannot, becauſe when you might you would not; ſo as through an ill will paſt, you haue loſt a good beeing preſent. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="160" type="part">
               <head>160.</head>
               <p>With GOD (who knoweth all thinges before they be done) a reſolued will to doe well, or ill, is reckoned for the deed done. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="161" type="part">
               <head>161.</head>
               <p>His braine is taken away whom GOD intendeth to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, leaſt hee ſhould by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence auert the intended plague.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="162" type="part">
               <head>162.</head>
               <p>He that makes an vndiſcreet Vow is fooliſh, and hee that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6974:33"/>keepes it is impious. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="163" type="part">
               <head>163.</head>
               <p>Alwayes breake vnlawfull Promiſes, and change vngodly Vowes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="164" type="part">
               <head>164.</head>
               <p>What good you haue vowed freely, that you are bound to performe juſtly. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="165" type="part">
               <head>165.</head>
               <p>A greedy Couetous man who deuoureth all like Hell, would haue none left aliue but himſelfe, that hee might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe all. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="166" type="part">
               <head>166.</head>
               <p>When God rewardeth Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, hee crowneth nothing but his owne Guifts: in the merite you doe nothing; in the worke, you worke alone; your Crowne is of God, your worke of your
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6974:34"/>ſelfe, yet not without Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="167" type="part">
               <head>167.</head>
               <p>Many good things doth God in Man, which man doth not; for Man doth nothing which God doth not, that Man may doe it. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="168" type="part">
               <head>168.</head>
               <p>All our merites are in ſuch manner the guifts of God, that Man is for the ſame more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to God, then God to Man. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="169" type="part">
               <head>169.</head>
               <p>Merite and Grace are at this oddes; that Grace will neuer enter, where Merite takes the vpperhand. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="170" type="part">
               <head>170.</head>
               <p>I know well, that by no ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, no merite, he ſhall euer bee
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6974:34"/>ſaued, who by the Paſſion of CHRIST is neuer moued. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="184" type="part">
               <head>184.</head>
               <p>Whenſoeuer Ideuoutly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and meditate the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of CHRIST, I ſhall be ſafe. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="172" type="part">
               <head>172.</head>
               <p>Not any one vpon earth is ſo rich, as hee deſireth nothing but God: and he is the Almes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of CHRIST, that is out of loue with the world. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="173" type="part">
               <head>173.</head>
               <p>Among thirtie thouſand men, ſcarſe one of thoſe ſhall repent truly, who driue of Repentance to the laſt caſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="174" type="part">
               <head>174.</head>
               <p>Hee is farre enough from Faith, that deferreth his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance till his Death. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="175" type="part">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:6974:35"/>
               <head>175.</head>
               <p>Repentance ſhould not bee late, not compelled, not fained, not deſperate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="176" type="part">
               <head>176.</head>
               <p>In a ſound man Penance is ſound, in a ſicke man it is ſicke, and in a dead man it is dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="177" type="part">
               <head>177.</head>
               <p>Reckon from <hi>Adam</hi> to the laſt Iuſt man, and you ſhall find none to bee ſaued, but by very hard and rough wayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="178" type="part">
               <head>178.</head>
               <p>Alwayes in your heart eſchew ill Company, and when you cannot auoyde them, conuerſe very warily amongſt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="179" type="part">
               <head>179.</head>
               <p>The vertue of the Sacraments, is not abated by the viciouſneſſe of the Prieſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="180" type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:6974:35"/>
               <head>180.</head>
               <p>I had rather vndergoe the torments of <hi>Caiphas, Herod,</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> then of a Prieſt that ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrates vnworthily. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="181" type="part">
               <head>181.</head>
               <p>Hee that tels a Lye, and hee that concealeth Truth, are both culpable, and guilty before God, the one for deſiring to doe hurt, and the other for not doing good. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="182" type="part">
               <head>182.</head>
               <p>If ſcandall ariſe from truth, it is rather to bee permitted, the truth pretermitted. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="183" type="part">
               <head>183.</head>
               <p>If I doe good with a good intention, though euill come thereof, yet it ſhall not bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to mee for ſinne. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="184" type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:6974:36"/>
               <head>184.</head>
               <p>Certainely hee cannot bee good, that would not bee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: For where hee begins not to be made better, there hee leaues off being good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="185" type="part">
               <head>185.</head>
               <p>No man is more incurable, then hee that thinkes himſelfe ſound when hee is truly ſicke, <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="186" type="part">
               <head>186.</head>
               <p>To ſtand and not to fall into ſinne, is Angelicall; to fall and riſe againe, is Humane; but to fall and ariſe, is Diabolicall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="187" type="part">
               <head>187.</head>
               <p>The Deuill hurteth by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, not by compulſion. <hi>Hug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="188" type="part">
               <head>188.</head>
               <p>The Deuill neuer tempts or
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6974:36"/>aſſaults thoſe, that are in his quiet poſſeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="189" type="part">
               <head>189.</head>
               <p>That ſinne which is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to, is no ſinne, but in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of exerciſe to vertue. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="190" type="part">
               <head>190.</head>
               <p>The worlds Mirth is vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht Wantomeſſe. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="191" type="part">
               <head>191.</head>
               <p>He that taketh vniuſtly, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome reſtoreth iuſtly. <hi>Iſid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="192" type="part">
               <head>192.</head>
               <p>He that is proud of his owne vertue, killeth himſelfe; not with a Sword, but with a Salue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="193" type="part">
               <head>193.</head>
               <p>Who often with their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will fall into offence, muſt ſometimes againſt their will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the ſmart of puniſhment. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="194" type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:6974:37"/>
               <head>194.</head>
               <p>God neuer forſakes man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man forſakes God. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="195" type="part">
               <head>195.</head>
               <p>It is monſtrous to behold, an eminent ſtate with a baſe minde; a high ſeate with a meane life; a nimble tongue with an idle hand; many wordes with no deeds; graue lookes with light actions; great authoritie with little conſtancie. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="196" type="part">
               <head>196.</head>
               <p>Bee alwayes doing of ſome good worke, that the Deuill may neuer finde you at leyſure for him. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="197" type="part">
               <head>197.</head>
               <p>God deferres the giuing of that wee aske, that we may aske more often, and more feruently.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="198" type="part">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:6974:37"/>
               <head>198.</head>
               <p>Hee that made you without you, will neuer ſaue you, or iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie you without you. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="199" type="part">
               <head>199.</head>
               <p>Doe not that euill your ſelfe, which you would not haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to doe. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="200" type="part">
               <head>200.</head>
               <p>As Iuſtice without Mercy, is not Iuſtice but Crueltie, ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour without Iuſtice, is not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour but folly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="201" type="part">
               <head>201.</head>
               <p>Correction without inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, is Tirannie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="202" type="part">
               <head>202.</head>
               <p>The laſt thinges euermore to bee remembred are Death, Iudgement, Hell, Glory; what is more horrible then Death? what more terrible then Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6974:38"/>what more intollerable then Hell? and what more joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then Glory. <hi>Bernardus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deo Gratias.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:6974:38"/>
            <head>Short Prayers or Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations vpon the laſt thinges, <hi>viz. Death, Iudgement, Hell, Glorie.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Vpon</hi> DEATH.</head>
               <p>OEternall GOD in whoſe hands the ſoules of the Iuſtare, and vnder whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection the torment of Death doth not touch them; take from my foule the diſordinate
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6974:39"/>loue of all viſible thinges, that in departing from them, it may haue no feeling of torment. O my Soule, if thou deſireſt that the bitterneſſe of Death ſhould not touch thee, loue not thoſe thinges that Death can take from thee; for if thou poſſeſſe them not with loue, thou ſhalt leaue them in Death and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Vpon</hi> IVDGEMENT.</head>
               <p>O How afflicted ſhall my poore Soule finde it felfe, with ſo ſtraight and rigorous an examination? O how aſtonied ſhall it bee with the euidence of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6974:39"/>ſo certaine and cleere proofe? O Eternall GOD, enter not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Iudgement with thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant; for none that liue, ſhall be juſtified in thy preſence. Feare O my Soule, although thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt no great ſinnes in thy ſelfe; for hee that is to examine and Iudge thee, is GOD, that ſeeth more then thou, and can finde them. Examine thy ſelfe with the greateſt rigour thou canſt, and judge ſeuerely thy ſelfe for the ſinnes thou ſhalt finde; for if thou judgeſt thy ſelfe with Dolour, thou ſhalt no more bee judged to Damnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:6974:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Vpon</hi> HELL.</head>
               <p>O Good IESVS, ayde mee to bewaile bitterly my ſinnes, that I may not goe to that tenebrous Land couered with the ſhadow of Death, the Land of thoſe that are in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, O touch mee with thy mercy, that being freed from the feares of Hell, I may euer enioy thee world without end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:6974:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Vpon</hi> GLORY.</head>
               <p>O Infinite GOD, center of my Soule, conuert mee to thee, that on thy eternall Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, I may partake of thy Glory; for thou madeſt mee for thee, and my heart is vnquiet till it come neere thee. O Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Father, ſeeing thou Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedſt mee, that I might Loue thee as a Sonne; giue me Grace for thine owne ſake, that I may loue thee as a Father. O onely begotten Sonne of the Father, and Redeemer of the world, ſeeing thou Createdſt mee and Redeemedſt mee, that I might
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6974:41"/>obey and imitate thee, ayde me that I may alwayes obey thee and imitate thee in all thinges. O moſt Holy Ghoſt, ſeeing that of thy goodneſſe thou diddeſt Create me to bee Sanctified, grant that it may bee for thine owne Glory, world without end.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6974:41"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
